已经把萨福克派去北部了吗
Have you dispatched suffolk to the north?
- 是的 陛下 - 您怎么对他说的
- Yes, your majesty. - what did you say to him?
我规劝他应该做至高无上的陛下之忠实骑士
I urged him as a true knight to his sovereign lord not
不应心存怜悯 而应毫无留情地弑杀那些不义叛军
To spare but frankly to slay plenty of these false rebels.
我对他说处死叛国者
I said to him there was no need for
根本不必客气
Courtesy in shedding the blood of traitors.
还有什么
And?
西班牙国王很快将派遣一名官方特使
The emperor will shortly be dispatching an envoy with authority to
前来与陛下商讨
Discuss with your majesty possible
玛丽小姐未来夫婿人选事宜
Candidates for the hand of the lady mary.
觉得此船如何
What do you think of this?
这是仪典船 威尼斯总督的官船
It's the bucintoro, the doge's ship.
建成之后 王后将乘坐此船前往加冕典礼
When it is built, the queen will ride in it to her coronation.
那必将是一次万世流芳的盛典
Then it will indeed be a memorable occasion.
当然 不过还得等到我儿出生之后
Of course, it will have to wait until after the birth of my son.
这是什么
What's that?
这是一份文扎 广泛传播
This is a pamphlet, widely distributed.
作者是陛下认识的 瑞金纳德·珀尔
Its author is reginald pole, of your majesty's acquaintance,
他新近被罗马主教任命为红衣主教
Who has lately been made a cardinal by the bishop of rome.
红衣主教 上面说什么
A cardinal? what does it say?
文中出言中伤陛下
It condemns your majesty in the vilest terms.
- 说我什么 - 说您是异教徒 以及
- As what? - as a heretic, and...
通奸者
...as an adulterer.
就这么心存感激
So much for gratitude...
还有更糟糕的
Unfortunately, there is more.
我的人还告诉我 这个珀尔红衣主教当下正以教皇使节的身份
My creatures tell me that the same cardinal pole is now in france,
出访法国 并私下面见了法王弗朗西斯
As papal legate and has been granted private audience with king francis.
很显然 他正试图挑唆法国及其他国家
Apparently, he is trying to persuade the french, and others,
出力协助叛军重起反对陛下
To help rekindle the rebellions against your majesty.
每年 威尼斯总督乘坐此船前往泻湖
Every year, the doge of venice travels out in this ship, into the lagoon,
面向大海重宣婚姻誓词
To renew his marriage vows with the sea.
与大海联姻
Marriage with the sea...
哪个君王不想要如此强大的情人
What prince does not aspire to have such an elemental mistress?
罗伯特·阿斯克先生
Mr. robert aske.
您被指控合谋颠覆国王陛下
You have been accused of conspiring to
为教会最高统治之罪
Deprive the king of his title of head of the church
并迫使陛下组建议会 以及
of seeking to compel him to hold a parliament; and finally,
策发起兵叛乱之罪
Of levying war against him.
而这皆是在陛下仁慈宽恕尔等叛乱之后
All after his majesty's gracious pardon was granted.
综上原因我们判您有罪
On all these counts we find you guilty as charged.
您将被送回约克郡
You are to be returned to york,
在你等疯狂作乱之地
Where you enjoyed your most frantic triumph
您将被施以绞刑
and there hanged in chains as a punishment
以惩您犯上作乱之重罪行
for your grievous sins against his majesty's highness and against this realm.
马已备好 公爵大人
Your horse is ready, your grace.
父亲
Father?
我儿
Son.
我知道您将履行您的职责
I know you will do your duty.
谢谢您 好了 去检查马匹吧
Thank you. now, go check on the horses.
我不指望您的祝福 凯瑟琳
I don't ask for your blessing, catherine.
只请您别心存诅咒送我走
Please don't send me away with your curse.
您是可敬之人
You are a man of honor,
我祈求上帝永远不要令我有理由诅咒和冒犯您
And I pray to god I shall never have cause to curse or disoblige you.
但我恳求您 仁慈一些
But I beg you, show mercy.
尤其是对那些无辜之人
Especially to the innocent.
拉尔夫·埃利卡爵士
Sir ralph ellerker.
拉尔夫爵士
Sir ralph...
您被指控参与最近一起阴谋叛乱
You are accused of taking part in the late insurrection that
恶意反对国王陛下及整个王国
So wretchedly offended his king's majesty and the whole realm.
鉴于您在法庭上的陈词
We have taken account of your deposition into the court
即您是出于对您自身及您家眷的人身安全
That you only joined the rebels out of fear
的考虑而参与叛乱
For your own life and the lives of your dependants.
同时鉴于您归案后发誓悔改
We also note your subsequent vows of contrition.
- 我们要求您签署此文书 - 这是什么
- We ask you to sign this. - what is it?
誓词
An oath.
您发誓对冒犯陛下
You swear that you are heartily sorry that you
参与叛乱诚心悔改
Have offended the king's highness in this rebellion.
您保证绝不集结非法军队
You promise never again to make unlawful assembly
并保证将此告知其余所有参与此事之人
And also promise to inform against anyone else who does.
从今往后 您将做我们的国王
From henceforth, you shall be a true and faithful subject unto our king,
至高无上的亨利八世
Our sovereign lord henry the eighth,
英国和法国国王
King of england and of france
英国教会在世间最高统治者的忠实子民 上帝保佑您
and on earth supreme head of the church of england, so help you god.
这样 国王陛下将仁慈地宽恕您
And in return, his majesty will grant you mercy.
- 那人还在动 - 杀了他
- That one's moving! -  finish him.
让路 那边的人
Make way!  you there!
你们都停下
Stop what you're doing!
别做了 听到没有
Stop your labors, do you hear?
让路
...of the king! make way!
停止劳动
Cease your labors!
停下 你
You stop it, you!
尔等皆乃叛国罪人
You are traitorous villains. all of you.
法律和天意俱规定尔等应归顺
You were bound, by law and by nature,
遵从国王陛下之旨意 而尔等却追随叛贼阿斯克
To obey the king's majesty and yet you followed the traitor aske
- 你才是叛国之人 - 犯下谋逆陛下之重罪
- You're the traitors!  - ...and rose in unholy rebellion against him!
尔等
And you
我来此是要向那些冥顽不灵
it is my purpose here to show a
不顺从最高尚庄严的陛下
Fearful example to those who would disobey
示以最严厉的惩罚 因为陛下
His most gracious and sacred majesty, who after all, in his mercy,
曾仁慈地宽恕过尔等
Granted you a pardon.
然而尔等却一意孤行违抗陛下
Whereupon you continued your willful disobedience and traitorous hearts.
综上原因 陛下不会再原谅尔等 上帝也不会
For these reasons, the king will not forgive you. and neither will god!
陛下
Your majesty...
夫人们
Ladies...
我们在天上的父 愿人都尊你的名为圣 愿你的国降临
Our father, who art in heaven hallowed be thy name, thy kingdom come,
愿你的旨意行在地上如同行在天上
Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
上帝啊 求您原谅您可怜的仆人 对您子民所犯的罪过
Please, lord, forgive thy poor servant, his trespasses against your flock.
阿斯克先生 我叫理查德·柯文
Mr. aske, my name is richard curwen.
我是授命牧师 我是来听您忏悔
I am an ordained priest, and I have come to hear your confession.
我可否如实相告 柯文先生
May I speak to you honestly, mr. curwen?
拜托您 不要辜负我的信任
Please, do not betray my trust.
绝不会 阿斯克先生
Never, mr. aske.
明日 我不仅要向陛下祈求原谅
Tomorrow, I must beg the forgiveness not only of his sacred majesty,
还要向克伦威尔和其他异教徒
But also of cromwell and the other heretics.
这让我备感屈辱
It sticks in my craw...
克伦威尔公开宣称我们所有北方人都是叛国者
Cromwell has openly said that all us northerners were traitors...
这令我气愤不已
It offended me so much.
他多次让我求饶 招供所谓的事实
And then, several times, he offered me a pardon, for confessing the truth!
克伦威尔是恶魔的使者 柯文先生
Cromwell is the devil's messenger, mr. curwen.
但我却必须求得他的宽恕
And yet, I must beg his pardon.
不然他们就会伤害我家人 此乃我绝不允许的
Or else they will hurt my family, and that I cannot allow.
不幸的是我妻子孩子将看着我被绞死
Bad enough that my wife and children will see me hanged,
尸首在铰链上慢慢腐烂
And left to rot in these chains.
阿斯克先生 您有何需要吗
Mr. aske, is there anything you need?
只要我能办到的 以此给予您最后的安慰
Anything I can get you, for solace?
再无任何慰藉了 柯文先生
There can be no solace, mr. curwen.
我再坐着独自抽泣会儿
I will sit here awhile, and weep,
之后我将投身到上帝的手中 被他的慈爱所包围
And thereafter deliver myself into god's hands and into his loving mercy.
以圣父及圣子及圣灵之名 阿门
In nomine patris, et filii, e et spiritus sancti. amen.
等等 有样东西
Wait. there is something.
缝在我领子里
Sewn into my collar there.
这是玛丽小姐给我的
I was given that by the lady mary.
出于对我们起义的支持 柯文先生 请将它交给我妻子
As you love our cause, mr. curwen, please hand it to my wife.
这能大大减轻她的痛苦
It will ease her burden greatly.
王后陛下驾到
her majesty the queen!
弗朗西斯·布莱恩爵士觐见
Sir francis bryan.
- 陛下 - 弗朗西斯爵士
- Majesty.  - sir francis.
瑞金纳德·珀尔昭显了他的野心
Reginald pole has shown us his true heart.
我命您前往巴黎 就法国国王对他热烈盛大的接待
I want you to go to paris, protest to the french king, on our behalf,
提出我们的抗议
For the solemn and pompous reception granted him.
遵旨
Majesty.
要求他将叛国者交给您
Ask him to deliver the traitor into your hands,
否则我们将会是永久的敌人
Or face the consequences and our perpetual enmity.
如果法王拒绝了呢
What if the king refuses?
您从前不也曾是间谍吗 弗朗西斯爵士
Were you not a spy once, sir francis?
曾经是 陛下 确实
I was, your majesty. indeed.
也绝非循规蹈矩之人
And a breaker of codes.
很好 或许您可以用一些您过往的伎俩
Well, perhaps you could revisit some of your old skills.
我本人乐意见到
I for one would like nothing better than
珀尔被五花大绑着送去加来
To have pole trussed up and taken to calais.
最好是活抓
And I'd rather alive than dead.
失陪
excuse me.
掌玺大臣在干吗
What is the lord privy seal doing?
我猜那些贵族想从他那购买
I imagine those nobles want to buy the
那些被废修道院的租契
Leases of some of the suppressed abbeys.
他们给克伦威尔先生什么回报呢
What are they giving mr. cromwell?
贿赂
Bribes.
克伦威尔先生早已十分富有
Mr. cromwell is already a rich man.
有人说他富可敌国
Some say the richest in the kingdom.
国王知道他们的勾当吗
Does the king know of this practice?
只要他能拿到10%的分红
He asks no questions.
国王便不再过问
As long as the crown receives its 10 percent share.
我们神圣的场所被人用来攫取财富 这难道不可悲吗
Is it not terrible that our sacred building be used like this for profit?
如果您非这么说 但您得了解其中的奥妙
If you say so.  then you have you have to understand how clever it is.
通过允许这些新兴贵族在国内购置产业
By allowing these new men to buy a stake in the kingdom
克伦威尔先生才能确保他们对国王及对他自己的忠诚
mr.Cromwell makes sure of their loyalty to the king and to himself.
- 别这样 - 我得走了
- stop!  - I have to go away.
- 所以呢 - 所以我等不及了
- So?  - so, I can't go until I've had you...
这太疯狂了
This is madness!
我就喜欢疯狂
I like madness.
不行 太危险了
No... it's too dangerous.
我丈夫会看到我们的 我万一怀上了怎么办
My husband might see us. what if I were to conceive your child?
那又怎样 很多女人都隐瞒了孩子的生父
So what? lots of women lie about the fathers of their children.
多你一个不多 让爱德华来养我的孩子吧
What does it matter to you? let edward raise my brat.
承认吧 女士 你也很喜欢这游戏吧
Admit it, lady, this is your game too.
那就来吧
Just do it...
约克城堡
York Castle
父亲 父亲
Father. father!
出去 快 把他们带出去
Out! go on, take them out!
我可怜的丈夫 我可怜的丈夫
Oh, my poor husband! my poor husband...
为什么 为什么他们要如此对你
Why? why have they done this to you?
为我祈祷吧
Pray for me.
我罪有应得
I deserve this.
不是 不是
No. no!
你罪不至此 别拉我
You do not deserve this! stop it!
你是好人 罗伯特·阿斯克
You are a good man, robert aske!
求你们为我祈祷吧 因为我触犯了上帝 国王
I ask you to pray for me for I have greatly offended god, the king,
以及天下苍生
And the world...
上帝 我因打破太多诫命而冒犯了他
God, I have offended by breaking his commandments in many ways.
我因触犯法律而冒犯了国王
And the king I have offended by breaking his laws
以上帝的旨意每个忠诚的子民都应遵从
to which every true subject is bound by the commandment of god.
我因自己的行为而冒犯了天下众生
And the world I offended since, for my actions,
让他们因此而丧生 失去家园和财物
So many have lost their lives, their lands, and their goods.
我恳请上帝宽恕吾王陛下
I ask forgiveness of his grace, his majesty.
也宽恕掌玺大臣 大法官大人
Also, my lord privy seal, my lord chancellor...
以及萨福克大人
And my lord of suffolk,
以我自由之心宽恕他对我犯下的罪行
Whose trespasses against me I also forgive with a free heart.
我热爱天下苍生
I love all the world.
此事之后我国疆土将一片祥和 宁静
This realm goes from good peace and quiet, daily,
日趋昌盛
To better and better.
叛国贼均已被处死
The traitors have been executed.
达西勋爵在塔山处死
The lord darcy at tower hill,
阿斯克则绞死在约克的地牢城堡之上
Aske hanged above the dungeon of the castle at york.
其余众人在伦敦行刑场处以极刑
The rest were executed at tyburn.
目前之势来看 所有的心头之患
So that, as far as we can perceive, all the cankered hearts...
均已铲除
Are weeded away.
诺曼底 法国
Normandy, France
就像这样 对了
Like this. exactly.
弗朗西斯·布莱恩爵士吗
e sir francis bryan?
容我自我介绍
Let me present myself.
我是塔利隆伯爵
I am count talleyrand.
法王弗朗索瓦派我来见您
His majesty king francois has sent me to meet you.
伯爵大人 让我为您介绍我的同伴
Count, Let me present my companion
托马斯·西摩先生 英国王后的兄弟
Mr. thomas seymour, the brother of the queen of england.
先生
Monsieur.
既然国王派您来见我们 您想必知道我们此行目的
So if the king has sent you, you know why we have come to france?
是的 是的 我知道
Oui, oui. I know.
我们希望贵国政府履行条约义务
And that we expect your government, under its treaty obligations,
逮捕反叛者瑞金纳德·珀尔
To apprehend the rebel reginald pole
并将其引渡至我方
and deliver him into our custody.
很不巧
Unfortunately,
国王陛下已给这位瑞金纳德·珀尔颁发了通行证
His majesty already granted safe passage to this reginald pole...
所以将他交予贵国 我国颜面何在
So it would have been dishonorable for him to hand him over.
不过 陛下在十天前曾修书致贵国国王
Nevertheless, he promised your king by letter, ten days ago,
信中承诺他将驱逐这位珀尔
That he would expel this pole.
- 他也做到了 - 那么珀尔现在人呢
- And so he did.  - then where is pole now?
据我说知 他被准许前往卡塞塔
All I know is that he was allowed to travel to caserta,
该地属西班牙国王的管辖之下
Under the emperor's jurisdiction.
在我看来你们处事的方式十分之古怪
It seems to me that your manner of proceeding has been very strange.
恐怕这会破坏两国国王之间的友谊
I fear it may lose your master the friendship of mine.
现在 我饿了
Now, I'm hungry.
晚安 伯爵大人
Good evening, count.
晚安 弗朗西斯爵士 先生
Good evening, sir francis. monsieur. e oh...
[法语]假日愉快
and bonnes vacances.
先生们
E monsieur...
你们的晚餐 请用
Gentlemen, your meal, if you please
没错 很好看
yes, very pretty.
那么 卡塞塔在哪儿 恕我愚昧
So, where's caserta? forgive my ignorance.
在意大利 那不勒斯的北边
In italy. north of naples.
是个可爱的老城
It's a nice old town.
告诉你汤姆 要是让我们抓着珀尔
I tell you this Tom, If we find pole,
我才不会捆他回去
I will not truss him up...
我要亲手结果他
I'm going to kill him with my own hands.
陛下 尤斯泰斯·查普伊斯大使阁下觐见
Your majesty his excellency, ambassador eustace chapuys.
阁下
Excellency.
国王陛下 王后陛下
Your majesties.
我主陛下向您们致以问候
The emperor sends you his love.
并赋予我重任 命我前来商讨
And he has charged me with the grave responsibility of negotiating
陛下的爱女玛丽小姐的亲事
With your majesty a suitable marriage for your daughter, the lady mary.
国王的人选为谁
Who does the king propose?
唐·路易斯殿下
His highness don luis,
葡萄牙王位继承人
The heir to the throne of portugal
也是我主王后伊莎贝拉之弟
and the brother of the emperor's wife, Isabella.
这个唐·路易斯 为人怎样
What type of man is he, this don luis?
他在各方面堪称完美
He is in every way a paragon.
品行端正 德操高尚
A man of great integrity and virtue.
骁勇善战
A man who has fought military campaigns and won.
学识渊博
A man with a profound knowledge of the world.
我女儿尚不晓世事
My daughter has no knowledge of the world.
她纯洁无瑕 天真无邪
she is an inocence, an innocent.
她超凡脱俗
And she is a very spiritual person.
这唐·路易斯将如何待她
How will this don luis treat her?
奉为圣女
Like a nun.
如此一来
In which case, alas,
也甭指望他们有后代了
it may be difficult for them to produce children.
阁下
Excellency.
西班牙国王为您提了一宗好亲事
The emperor has suggested a splendid offer for your hand.
唐·路易斯殿下时年二四
His highness don luis is twenty four years old,
出身高贵 家财万贯
From a very rich and distinguished family.
接着说
Go on.
据说他在西班牙国王宫廷深得人心
I am told he is a great favorite at the imperial court.
深得女人芳心
With... women?
是所有人
With everyone.
因为他卓越不凡风流倜傥且斯文有礼
Because he is so honorable and gallant and good natured.
那他
Is he...
长相端正吗
...good looking?
是
Yes.
我亲眼见过他
I have seen him myself.
他玉树临风 有一头乌发和炯炯有神的蓝眼睛
He is tall, with very dark hair but piercing blue eyes.
我相信您母亲 愿主安抚她的灵魂
I am sure that your mother, god rest her soul,
也会应允这门亲事
would have approved.
宫里的人都在议论您
And everyone at court is talking about you.
他们说王后劝服了陛下
They say the queen has persuaded his
将恢复您为合法继承人
Majesty to reinstate you to the succession.
可怜那罗伯特·艾斯克
Poor robert aske...
据说他仍负枷 悬尸示众
I was told his body is still hanging, trimmed in chains, for all to see.
我不能只顾自己幸福
I should not be thinking of my own happiness.
好心的小姐 您追求幸福是理所应当
Sweet madam, you have every right to think of it.
大人们 身为教会领袖
Your graces, as head of the church,
我为你们无法在教旨与修行这等
I am vexed by your inability to agree on
基本问题达成共识深感失望
The fundamental issues of doctrine and practice.
我聆听你等的传道
I listen to your sermons.
不时觉得 你们的福音宣教
And sometimes, I find them full of...
毫无头绪 无法被认可
Evangelical excesses which have never been Agreed upon
更不能为英国教众接受
and have no place in the church of england.
大人们 我要教会内部达成一致
Your graces, I want unity and agreement in our church.
不要再有教义分歧
I want diversity of opinion ended,
我要推行统一的教宗
and uniformity imposed.
因此
Therefore,
我特命你等成立委员会
I command you to establish a commission amongst
拟定我国教会之基本教义
Yourselves to determine the basic articles of our faith.
王后陛下她
It's her majesty!
- 何事 - 陛下
- What is it? -  your majesty.
宝贝儿 什么事
Sweetheart, what is it?
一切正常
Everything is all right.
来
Come.
感觉到了么
Can you feel it?
他在动
It's moving!
在踢我呢
It's kicking!
我能感觉到 他结实着呢
I can feel it. he feels strong!
爱德华 我儿
Edward, my son...
很强壮的
Be strong.
赌一克朗我下一条我钓到
A crown I catch the next one.
怎么了 父亲
What is it, father?
- 你没看到他吗 - 看到谁
- Can't you see him? -  see who?
就在那儿
Over there...
你看不到吗
Can't you see him?
噢 看啊
Well, look!
告诉我 你能见到他
Tell me you can see him.
那男子
That man...
他在那儿
He's there!
你看到他了 是不是
You can see him, can't you?
看在老天的份上 你看到他了么
For god's sake, do you see him?
没多久 王后的胎儿就足月了
In a while, the queen will come to full term.
我要您去筹备我儿降生的庆祝会
I want you to organize the celebrations for the birth of my son.
深感荣幸
I would be honored.
庆祝会要无比壮观 在王国各地
I want them to be truly spectacular; te deums and
礼拜颂歌 燃起焰火
Bonfires throughout the kingdom,
还有免费畅饮
and free wine for everyone.
并比试剑术
And tournaments.
前王后若诞下王子 我也曾打算办剑术比赛
I had planned a tournament for the birth of a prince with my last queen.
但最后只得作罢
But it had to be cancelled.
这回陛下可没理由不办了
This time your majesty will have no reason to cancel it.
我另有一事请教陛下
May I ask your majesty's opinion on another matter?
近期的叛乱 感谢上帝
In the recent rebellion which, thank god,
陛下已镇压
your majesty has now suppressed,
并已处死首恶
And the worst rascals properly put to death
叛贼谋反主要是为
great cause was made by
反对掌玺大臣
Some against the lord privy seal,
此次祸端多因归咎于他
who in some quarters was blamed for it.
说实话 我们觉得他身陷凶险
Frankly we thought him in danger,
当然我们深信错不在他
whilst trusting he was not.
叛乱分子要克伦威尔的首级
It was the rebels who demanded mr. cromwell's head.
既然如此 我们就越要保住他
And by doing so, they saved it.
- 罗切福特夫人 - 陛下
- Yes, lady rochford? - majesty.
利尔斯夫人致信于我
Lady lisle has written to me asking
问我王后陛下能否在您的宫廷
if your majesty might find a place in
给她两个女儿中的的一个安排职位
Your household for one of her two daughters.
我告诉她会向您禀报
I told her I would mention it to you.
您是否警告过利尔斯夫人宫廷生活
Have you warned the lady lisle that life at court is full of pride, envy,
充满傲慢 嫉妒 轻蔑和嘲笑
Scorn, and derision?
如果您已经告诫过她们 就让她们来吧
If you have, then send them to me.
我会选一个
And I'll choose one of them.
请记住 准备两套衣服
And remember,there must be two sets of clothes.
一套用绸缎做 另一套用锦文布
one of satin, the other of damask.
是的 夫人
Madam.
米索顿女士 请帮我解开长袍
Lady misseldon, help me unlace my gown.
衣服好像每分每秒都在变小
It seems to grow tighter by the hour.
若我有什么不测 请为我安慰陛下
If anything should happen to me, be a comfort to his majesty.
是 陛下
Majesty.
夫人 陛下
Madam! majesty!
别慌 女士们
Do not be alarmed, ladies.
我想分娩时辰到了 玛丽女士
But I think my time has come. lady mary?
陛下
Majesty
请发誓守着我 不要离开
please swear that you will stay with me now and not forsake me.
我发誓
I do promise.
那就好了 快去请助产士
Then all will be well. go fetch the midwife.
到床上来
Come to the bed.
陛下
Majesty?
是时候了吗
Well? is it time?
是的 陛下
Yes, your majesty.
请我的御医去照看她
Send my physician to watch over her.
- 是 陛下 - 再请彼奇大人过去
- Yes, your majesty. - and fetch my lord beauchamp.
- 加德纳主教也一并请去 - 是 陛下
- And bishop gardiner. - majesty.
再派些使者到城里去告知这个消息
And send some heralds into the city to tell them the news!
还有克伦威尔 通知克伦威尔
And cromwell. tell mr. cromwell...
告诉他 所有事宜留待商榷
Tell him... tell him that whole worlds hang in the balance.
生产时间到了 生产时间到了
It's happening! it's happening!
祈求耶稣 请赐予我们王子
I pray jesus, if he wills, to send us a prince!
让我看看
Let me have a look now.
求主引领我们 给我们救助 阿门
Domine adjutor et protector noster, adjuva nos. amen.
深呼吸 陛下 很好
Breathe deep, your majesty. good.
- 玛丽女士 - 是的 夫人
- Lady mary. - yes, madam.
那个盒子
The box.
它曾属于您母亲
It used to belong to your mother.
我想她与我们同在
I think she is here, with us.
我全心全意的相信 她会帮助您的
I believe with all my heart she will help you.
全能永恒的主啊 请对病痛者发发慈悲吧
Almighty and everlasting god, mercifully look upon our infirmities,
当我们陷入危险 孤立无援时
And in all our dangers and necessities,
请伸出您的手来帮助我们保护我们
Stretch forth thy right hand to help us and defend us,
我们的主耶稣
through christ our lord.
使劲儿 四指了
You've got to push. all four fingers.
很好 陛下
Good, your majesty.
明天将全城举行一场庄严的游行
Tomorrow there will be a solemn procession through the city,
所有人为王后祈祷 如果她还在生产中
All to pray for the queen if she is still in labor with child.
如果她还在生产中 上帝保佑我们
If she is still in labor with child, god help us...
我害怕会失去他们两个
I think to lose them both.
我诚心归顺上帝
I am reconciled with god.
我没有做违背良心的事情
I have done nothing against my conscience.
听命于国王就是听命于上帝
To serve the king is to serve god.
我怀孕了
I am with child.
她还没有好转
She is no better.
求您了 夫人 别放弃啊
Please, my lady. don't give up.
看在耶稣的份儿上 别放弃
Please, for the love of jesus, don't give up!
陛下 我和御医们商量了
Your majesty, I talked to the physicians.
他们认为不剩多少时间了
In their opinion there is not a great deal of time left.
如果他们不尽快为王后切腹取出胎儿
The baby is likely to die unless they
胎儿很可能会死
Cut open the queen's belly to release it.
如此一来 王后本人很可能就保不住了
In which case, it is almost certain that she herself will die.
陛下您得尽快决定
Your majesty may thus have to decide soon
是保母亲 还是保孩子
Between the life of the mother or of the child.
恳求主怜悯我们 恳求主怜悯我们
Kyrie, eleison;  kyrie, eleison.
耶稣怜悯我们 耶稣怜悯我们
Christe, eleison;  christe, eleison.
让我过去
Let me pass!
陛下
Your majesty.
王后陛下产下了 一名健康的男孩
Her majesty is delivered... of a healthy son.
我有儿子了
I have a son?
I have a son!
是的 陛下
Yes, your majesty.
您有儿子了
You have a son.
英国未来的国王
And a future king of england.
祝福你 我的宝贝
Bless you, sweet child.
爱德华 我们的儿子
Edward, our son...
以上帝 圣母玛利亚和圣乔治之名 祝福你
Bless you, child, in the name of god, the virgin mary, and st. george.
他是个可爱的王子
He's a sweet prince.
- 没错 - 而且他是我们的弟弟
- Yes, he is. - and he's our brother.
国王盼儿子盼好久了
The king has waited a long time for a son.
但他仍然爱我们
But he still loves us.
男孩更重要一些 伊丽莎白
A boy is more important, elizabeth.
我看未必
I don't think so.
以上帝 圣子和圣灵的名义
In the name of the father, son, and holy ghost
我为爱德华施洗礼
I baptize thee edward.
但愿上帝会在你有生之年庇佑你
May god bless and keep you all the days of your life,
给予你他无穷的恩惠
And give you abundantly his grace,
我们的主耶稣 阿门
through jesus christ our lord. Amen
阿门
Amen.
全能慈悲的主啊
God, of his almighty and infinite grace,
请赐予至高无上的王子
Give and grant good life and long to the right high,
同时也是康沃尔公爵及切斯特伯爵
right excellent,and noble prince edward, duke of cornwall and earl of chester,
我们最威严高尚的国王亨利八世的爱子
most dear and entirely beloved son to our most dread and gracious lord,
爱德华王子长命百岁 永享尊荣
king henry the eighth.
王后的病情在急速恶化
The queen's health has rapidly deteriorated.
昨晚 她已经能够排便
Yesterday evening she had a loosening of
当时我们感觉肯定可以救她
The bowels and we felt sure we could save her...
但夜里她发热更严重了
But during the night her fever grew worse again.
我们试了所有的办法
We have tried everything we know.
但是 王后仍然越来越虚弱
But... her majesty continues to weaken.
这是产褥热
It's childbed fever.
我知道这个是因为我母亲是这么去世的
I know because my mother died of it.
出去 退下
Get out... leave.
陛下
Majesty.
别走
Don't go.
求求你 别走
Please, don't go.
就因为你兑现了你的承诺
Just because you have done everything that you promised,
求你别离开我
Please don't leave me.
你充满着恻隐之心
You are the milk of human kindness
是我黑暗世界里的明灯
and the light in my dark, dark world.
没有了你 人生就是荒漠 是旷野
Without you life is a desert; a howling wilderness.
上帝啊 显显慈悲吧 别把她从我身边带走
Please god, in your mercy, don't take her away from me.
我的儿子需要他的母亲
My son needs his mother...
我也需要我的王后
And I need my queen.